this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
[Music]
are you a software engineer developer
consultant architect manager no matter
what your role is we want to hear from
you please take a minute to complete our
listener survey to help us make SE radio
even more relevant to you
just go to
se-radio.net
survey2023 to share with us that's
se-radio.net survey2023
thanks for your support of the show
hi this is Philip Winston for software
engineering radio today my guest is
Lucas fiddle Lucas is the founder and
CEO of PG analyze he has worked as a
software engineer in the postgres
ecosystem for the last 15 years
including as a founding engineer at the
startup cytus data which was acquired by
Microsoft in 2019 prior to that he was
an early engineer at product hunt which
was acquired by angelist in 2016.
postgres is one of the most popular
database systems in the world with over
30 years of active development today
we'll discuss postgres database
performance along with the PG analyze
tools
we'll start by introducing postgres and
PG analyze and then tour through various
postgres performance related features
such as indexing query scaling
maintenance and if we have time stored
procedures
welcome to the show Lucas and can you
tell us what is postgres in your point
of view
of course and thank you Phillip for
having me so postgres in general is you
know if you're an application engineer
you might think of postgres as the thing
that just does work behind the scenes
for you so postgres is a relational
database system it's just turned 27
years old so it's you know old enough to
drive a car and to write to its own
thesis and postgres was started at the
University of Berkeley 27 years ago and
it is extremely popular today right so
most likely if you're using an
application today postgres will be the
backing data store behind it the main
data in the database is going to be
stored in postgres in many cases and so
really to me postgres you know is one of
the most important open source
Technologies today what types of
applications does postgres excel at I
know it's a very general purpose
database but if there is an area of what
it's most known for
sure and I think there isn't necessarily
one type of data that you can store in
postgres I think generally what I've
seen is that for system of record type
data right so if where you let's say you
build an application and you're thinking
where can I actually store the data for
my application that's where postgres
Excel set bubble postgres is also good
at this being extensible so for example
post GIS is a very popular extension for
postgres that allows you to work with
geospatial data in postgres more
recently there's an extension called PG
Vector which lets you store Vector data
in postgres so you can you know work
with your AIML embedding type data with
postgres and so that's really the power
of postgres is that flexibility of being
able to support individual data types
that are useful for particular use cases
yeah I'm glad you mentioned post just
that was going to be one of my questions
I think when we get into the specifics
we might come back to post just and how
it impacts indexes and and other things
how about the cloud computing angle on
postgres I know Amazon has this RDS
service and Aurora is a type of database
are these postgres under the hood or are
they compatible with postgres yeah and
it's a good question so you know
generally you could run postgres
yourself in a virtual machine right so I
think what I would always emphasize
similar to you know the Linux kernel you
can just run Linux yourself right you
can build it yourself but what's
interesting of course is that roughly I
would say 15 years ago database as a
service kind of took off as a concept
and so I would say one of the most
prominent early starters in that space
was Heroku postgres Heroku these days
unfortunately not that many people are
using it anymore but it I think was one
of the first places that really brought
developer experience as the main thing
that they cared about in the experience
and so hero post was a managed database
service where instead of you having to
run your own virtual machine you were
actually able to kind of have just a API
that you could use API in this case
meaning you know you run your SQL
queries against the connection string
and so nowadays of course AWS and Amazon
RDS Service as well as Amazon Aurora is
probably the most popular postgres as a
service database managed databases you
could find what's notable there I would
say is that Aurora for example is a fork
of postgres so what they've done
essentially is they've you know taken to
open source postgres code which is BSD
license so like very deliberately
licensed and so they took that code and
they essentially made modifications to
the storage engine and part of the
motivation there was to increase
resiliency so when you have you know
different availability zones in AWS they
want to have a better concept of how the
kind of resilient architecture of the
database works and so Aurora is
essentially a very tight to aws's
approach of doing things versus RDS is
there it's still a forked version but
it's less you know much less patched
doesn't Aurora and so if you want to be
portable right if you want to have your
postgres work similarly on gcp on AWS on
Azure then it's certainly better to in
my opinion focus on you know the RDS
type service or Google for example you
have Google's lodb service which is
again their fourth version of postgres
and they also have Cloud SQL which is
their more standard postgres and so I
think oftentimes it's actually better to
not stray too much into the forks of
postgres because you get kind of special
behaviors that are unique to each
provider's infrastructure this might be
self-evident but why is database
performance so important
sure and I would say I mean it kind of
comes back to the postgres being your
source of Truth your system of record
meaning that a lot of cases when your
application is wants to answer a web
request for example right it will have
to ask a database and we'll have to ask
a database like postgres and so one
thing I saw this morning for example is
so Google announced a new kind of mode
of measuring page performance right so
they're now saying I think anything
that's lowered in 200 milliseconds on
you know a mobile device is actually a
slow page and they will rank it less now
you could think if that was an
application right so if you were
actually like querying customer data for
example ultimately what you would have
is a web request that goes to a postgres
database and that request is a query
right and so the query if that is slowed
into it in a milliseconds you would by
definition fail that you know kind of
performance test and so database
performance matters because ultimately
it is actual web performance right this
is actually end user performance in many
cases and so whether it is measurements
that Google makes whether it is you know
actual end users being frustrated
because your application is slow
database performance matters because it
essentially builds a better experience
for your end users of your applications
and we'll get into this later but
certainly your ability to scale might be
hampered by your database performance so
things are working fine when you have 10
000 users but then you have a million
users and performance falls apart so I
think that's something we'll discuss in
a little bit but I wanted to mention
from a previous show that I'll cite soon
SQL is a declarative language what are
the implications for this as far as
performance it seems like it's related
to the fact that you can't necessarily
see what steps or instruct the database
in what steps to take you have to just
count on it figuring that out yeah I
think that's a great question so I think
you're essentially stating what you want
right you're telling the database please
give me this data from this table and
filter it in this way or order it sorted
in this way but you're not necessarily
telling it how to do that and so it is
both I think the power of database but
also of course the downside which is the
database will make that choice for you
right so you can to clear your intent
and the database will find a way to
answer that query to answer that intent
of yours that you declared using the
query language now of course this
relates to index usage right in all
these other topics but I think really it
is a fundamental nature of how databases
work especially relational databases
work is that you're not just saying I'm
calling this method which works exactly
this way but instead you're saying I
want this data and I want it filtered
and grouped and sorted this way figure
it out for me
so let's start talking about PG analyze
when did you start working on this
project and what was the original
motivation at the time sure so teaching
allies I started I think was it like 11
years ago now so 2012 as a site project
initially and it kind of grew out of my
own I would say frustrations with
working with postgres so I first worked
with postgres when I co-founded the
company back in 2007 back in Europe and
we were doing like social media blogging
type sites and at the source of that
site was a postgres database and so back
then there was just no good tooling to
understand why our site was slow right
like we had essentially bad used
experiences and we didn't understand why
and so a couple years later right I kind
of got together with somebody I had
worked with at the time who in my
perspective was a postgres expert and so
I essentially went and said you know how
could we make a product out of this how
could we say for example One Challenge
at the time was how do I know what is
slow in the database right so I see the
CPU utilization of my database but how
can I actually know what is taking time
and we could really only observe you
know a slow page load but how do we
actually know it is this particular
query and so what postgres introduced
around that time is an extension called
PG stat statements and what that
extension does is it measures all the
queries that get executed on the
database site and so the reason that's
so important right is because you can
just ask the database give me all the
queries that you've seen and how long
they've taken right and then you can
from that decide what to optimize which
index is to create and so what PG
analyze essentially in its very first
iteration did was literally just showing
that data right it was a you know very
ugly looking bootstrap site that at the
time was the way to do things and so it
was literally just pulling that data and
showing it in a quick view it didn't
work as a business really in the
beginning it was more a kind of project
just for for our own benefit essentially
but already that was really useful it's
just having that data of the query which
queries have run and also over time so
you can say well yesterday at 5 PM we
saw a spike in query activity why was
that right was why was it suddenly
slower and so that was really the
initial focus of the product
so I think one thing he said there is
that it's the load on the database or
the types and amounts of queries that
are going to determine the performance
in some cases so having a slow query
that you almost never run is maybe not a
problem but having millions of queries
that are have a performance issue is is
obviously a much bigger problem
so can you talk about postgres built-in
explain feature and I guess explain
analyze and what does PG analyze do that
goes beyond these sure yes if we think
back just in terms of what you what we
talked about earlier right in terms of
SQL being a declarative language right
and so you're you're not really telling
the database how to do something and so
the explain feature in postgres what
that does is it will explain to you what
the database will do right so generally
when postgres you know gets a query it
first does the parsing of the query it
then does what's called parse analysis
to actually say well these like tables
you're referencing are actually these
physical tables in database and then
just planning and then there's execution
now the part where postgres essentially
has a lot of choice it's making is that
planning process right because in the
planning process postgres will decide
which indexes to use how to join your
tables which you know kind of how to
group things how to sort things right
all these decisions are being made in a
planning process and so with the explain
kind of statement does in postgres is it
will show you the the query query plan
that is being determined in that
planning phase and would have also
showed you the costs that postgres
determines so generally when postgres
makes a decision on which way to query a
table right which index to use or how to
join it will do that based on cost and
costs are essentially just units that
postgres is using so they're not time or
anything they're literally just you know
this has cost five this has cost 10 I'll
choose cost five because it's less cost
essentially and so when you do just
explain without analyze really what this
does it just shows you the output of the
planning stage right it just shows you
the result of planning the good thing
about just bear explain is that it's
really fast because planning is always
intended to be fast right like postgres
will not spend a lot of time finding the
perfect plan because then each of your
queries will be slow instead what it
does is it essentially does the best
effort search in a lot of cases and so
explain will give you that even for very
complex queries you will quickly get the
explain plan or the query plan by just
putting explain in front of your SQL
statement now explain analyze on the
other hand that actually runs the query
and to explain analyze is very useful if
you want to know which portion of the
query took which runtime the thing to
know about explain analyze and this
might not be this might be not obvious
so I mentioned it now which is it has
overhead to run explain analyze itself
and so there's some settings you can use
to reduce that overhead but one of the
challenges is if you're measuring things
to explain analyze you kind of in a
sense you're measuring a Target that
also is not the same as the usual
execution time right so that there's
some intricacies there the other thing
that we've explained analyzed that's
really useful is explain analyze buffers
so buffers is a special option that you
can pass when you're doing explain
analyze and the reason it's so useful is
because it shows you how much data the
database is loading so you cannot just
see the runtime of the query and the
individual parts of the query but you
can also see how many bytes of data
essentially are being loaded how many
blocks of data and so that is super
useful because ultimately a lot of times
the bottlenecks in a query are IO
problems right and so oftentimes you end
up just having slow i o because you're
going to network storage in the cloud
and so understanding which part of your
query is doing that I O is super
important now what we do in PG analyze
is we actually integrate with an
extension called autoexplain now Auto
explain is really useful because instead
of you running these commands
interactively right you connecting to a
database you actually get the queries
recorded by the database itself so
autoexplain says if the threshold for
example is let's say one like I said one
second for example each query that is
slower than one second will get logged
to the postgres log now we do in pure
channel is we pick up those log entries
so PG analyze as a product we'll just
parse the logs continuously and then
grab these log entries that say this
query took this long and here was the
execution plan there's various settings
that we recommend tuning for all to
explain so it's you know safe to use in
production but generally you know people
have reported I would say in the most
expensive version of it between one and
three percent overhead but it's
definitely you know closer to one
percent if you use the right settings
and it's just so useful because you know
the exact plan that executed at the time
of your query being slow not just the
plan that you see when you run a query
right now
so give us a sense of using PG analyze
is it primarily visualizing this Auto
explain are there completely different
features that people run say for looking
at memory or disk or or what's the basic
set of options if I'm running PG analyze
for sure yeah and I'll speak to I would
say how I look at the system right
because I we use speech analyst
ourselves to optimize our own database
which I generally find is the best way
to build a product is you know use it
yourself and so I think first and
foremost right it shows you data that
you don't really see otherwise right so
oftentimes today what you would see in
your cloud provider dashboard is like a
very high level graph that says you know
this is the super utilization right
maybe you'll see something like active
sessions but you don't really see that
detailed level of detail that um shows
you and so usually when I use PG analyze
I would use our kind of query overview
to see which queries are the most active
and then I would jump into an individual
query now for each of those queries I
can get the performance over time again
that is what we reference to earlier PG
stat statements that's really data that
comes from PG stat statements now where
I think PG analyz is unique and I think
it's even today I mean this is true five
years ago but it's still true today what
we do well is we actually link together
these statistics table so the future
stat statements type data and the actual
postgres log data right so sometimes
with challenging is when you have these
auto-explain plans they're in your logs
but you'd have to just read through log
files and it becomes very tedious right
and so what we do is we actually pull
those up into the query page so that you
see all the explain plans that were
recorded for the query right in that
specific query page and so that saves
you a lot of time because you don't have
to go looking for log files there's of
course many other features that we've
added to PG analyze again from our
perspective of using it as well as from
customers kind of reporting things one
other thing I think that's noteworthy in
the context of query performance is what
we call query tags so one challenge that
as an application engineer that you
sometimes have is SQL queries are not
really what you're thinking in right
you're thinking in orm calls right the
Orem kind of abstracts the SQL query
away from you and so what we've added is
a way to essentially you tag your
queries with the location in which kind
of the query originates right so you can
say this line source code this file
maybe this name of this particular
controller in my application and in the
query tags feature will highlight that
on the query page and so that way I can
actually understand better which party
application is causing me slowness
how do you think about
database performance compared to General
application performance or maybe
operating system performance it seems
like there's a lot of
similarities but there's differences
also
yeah and I think in in terms of tooling
is maybe one way to answer this question
right so for example we ourselves use a
combination of PG analyze and Sentry for
our own performance monitoring so when
we want to look at this from a kind of
application-centric perspective we would
look first and Century now what century
would show us is a trace for example
right so it would tell us this
particular web request took this amount
of time but really that stops at the
individual SQL query and so if I'm
thinking of individual users
experiencing a slow web experience I
would start there and then I would go
into PG allies to really do the Deep
dive and really find out why the query
was slow right why you know like was
this a pattern right is this query
always so I think from an operational
perspective we for example have our own
grafana dashboards as well and so I
think you know some of the high level
metrics I think systems like rafana or
AWS cloudwatch are best suited for
because they kind of give you that
summary view over a lot of different
pieces of infrastructure and so to me
really I think it's a combination like
use the right tool for the right task
right so if you're trying to drill into
your database use something it's
database specific if you're trying to
understand what you know end user
transactions are slow use an APM tool if
you're trying to get a sense of your
infrastructure use something that's good
for infrastructure monitoring I think
it's really good to use purpose-built
tooling versus something that's generic
that doesn't really do a good job
yeah so it sounds like you're talking
about monitoring up and down the stack
kind of at all levels how about for
postgres itself are there other
performance monitoring or optimization
tools that you use yourself
yeah good question I mean there's a lot
of projects in the open source if you're
ever interested in this you know from a
non-biased perspective right I always
have my own biases of course there's a
good list under postgres Wiki that just
lists out all the different monitoring
tools I think what I use myself again it
kind of comes back to explain I would
say right so when I when I am looking at
a slow query what it would usually do I
would try to understand why it's slow
right now I would maybe look at a
recorded explain plan a PG analyze but
then I would also if I want to
experiment but if I want to try out
different variants of the query like
maybe I'll remove a part of the query
see if it performs differently usually
what I would do is just run and explain
on the database directly and I think I
would say that's really the most common
tool that I use of course there's you
know many Alternatives that people might
also use for other parts I'll give you
one example so for example in PG analyze
we have a feature to do log monitoring
but a very popular tool to do this in
open source world without the product
like which analyst is called PG Badger I
think PG Badger is a great tool I've
used it in the past I no longer use it
because my channel it solves that for me
but I think there is obviously a lot of
great projects in the post ecosystem
that are created by individuals just
because they're scratching their own
Edge essentially solving their own
problems so always good to find things
like that I'll include links to these
applications in the show notes what
language or languages was PG analyzed
written in is it a part of it a postgres
extension or how does it have access to
the postgres specific data
yeah it's a good question let me see so
I'm by trade mostly I would say well I
started with C plus personally but
there's no Surplus Plus in future
analytics luckily there's a bunch of C
which I'll get to in a moment we started
with Ruby I think initially and so a lot
of the web application that we have is
both built in Ruby we recently started
adopting rust so a lot of the kind of
performance processing that we're doing
is in Rust so the way to think about it
right we'll be doing is you have your
database server right and we have a
component that runs on your server or
close to your server in the case of
managed service and then that component
sends data to our service that data gets
processed gets stored in postgres
database ultimately and then that data
gets queried you know in our web UI and
so kind of the way our stack looks like
is that component that runs in your
environment that's actually go
application for historic reasons then
you know that sends into our statistics
processing that's rust and then we have
a web interface that's built in Ruby it
to me it again comes back to using the
best tool for the job right so I think
for example go the big benefit is that a
lot of cloud providers actually publish
SDK case forego rust for example the I
think the AWS rust SDK is actually in
pretty good shape now but a year ago it
was still experimental and so you
couldn't really access the AWS apis in a
stable way in Rust versus go you know
just works well and so go was a good fit
there think of rust for example in our
backhand it really comes down to
Performance right so how do we make sure
that we have you know the least overhead
essentially when we're pulling in these
statistics and we're running our
analysis and so that's that's what kind
of thrust sets and then Ruby I think is
just very convenient for kind of basic
crowd type applications where you're
just showing data and you have like
stuff like you know users that sign in
and things like that Ruby and Ruben
rails is just good at that
so is the C part you mentioned is that
an extension yeah sorry let me actually
let's fix it up so the by intentionally
said we don't want to build an extension
because the problem with extensions and
that is true today and hopefully will
not be true at some point in the future
if you're using a managed service
provider like AWS RDS you can't actually
use your custom extensions right so if I
today went and I created a custom
extension I would have to then ask AWS
to enable that extension on their system
and that is a long process and they
usually do it based on you know
customers requesting it not me you know
as an individual just requesting it and
so it's very hard to get a custom
extension to be adopted by the cloud
providers there's some efforts recently
to improve on that but what we've
essentially said early on is we don't
think that it's the right approach to
build our own extension because it
limits our adoption essentially or use
and so we did instead we are actually
using portions of the postgres source in
our own application so I think roughly
six years ago I first created a library
called PG query and what PG query does
is it actually pulls the parser from
postgres and makes it a standalone
library right so you could think of when
postgres gets your query it as mentioned
earlier it first does the parsing then
it does the parse analysis then does the
active planning then the execution
instead of very first step of parsing is
very important because when you're
trying to understand what is a query
even doing right like which columns this
is referencing which tables is
referencing you kind of need that parse
Street at that first step determines
that's what PG query does is it just
plucks out that particular portion of
postgres puts it in a C library and then
also has a ruby wrapper around it so
that what we could do with PG query was
in our Ruby application at the time we
were able to essentially just call the
parser and say this query what is it
actually doing right is it an update
statement is it what is it updating
what's the table name which columns is
it filtering by it's all that very
in-depth analysis we need to essentially
extract the parser so is PG analyzed
today strictly a service or is there
also an open source package that you can
install or how does that work he has
essentially a combination so we open
source parts of our libraries that we
built so PG query being the best example
of this so PG query is open source if
you have a use case for parsing queries
yourself you can just run PG query in
your own application and people have
done all kinds of things for that fun
fact if you install gitlab gitlab
bundles PG query as part of their
installed because they're using it in
some you know part of their own tooling
but PG analyze as a product is a
commercial product so we are a small
company we are bootstrapped so no we see
money it's just our own money from you
know essentially building a product
selling it to customers and so to make
that sustainable we've essentially
chosen that you know parts are open
source that we find are generally useful
but then the PG analyst product itself
is a commercial product
now before we dive into a postgres
performance specific sort of tips and
tricks and and just learning about it I
would like to reference three
software engineering episodes that dealt
with postgres that are useful you might
find useful episode 454 Thomas Richter
on postgres as an olap database
from 2021 episode 362 Simon Riggs on
Advanced features of postgres 2019 and
episode 328 Bruce momjin on the postgres
query planner 2018 which I found
particularly interesting the way he
discussed that in detail so one of those
shows mentions olap can you talk about
the difference between oltp and olap
which is I guess the difference between
transactions and analytics particularly
with respect to Performance and
performance monitoring of course yeah so
generally the way I would think about it
right if you have your typical web
application today that you know let's
say it's a CRM tool or something right
that would be a typical OTP application
right so OTP applications have a lot of
fast queries they're you know usually
the system of record type system where
you're serving a web request for example
that is a typical oltp system now an
olap system on the other hand would be
something more like a data warehouse
right so where you're trying to do
business analytics as an intelligence
type queries where you're trying to say
how many of my customers have done this
in this time frame and you're looking
just a lot of Records right now postgres
the good news is postgres can do both
right so postgres is it can be used both
as an OTP system as well as an OLED type
system generally though I would say
postgres will excel at oltp type
workloads all that workloads can be it
can make sense to use more purpose-built
databases in some cases particularly for
example one thing to note about postgres
is way of storing data is it's generally
a row based format and so row based
formats make a lot of sense if you're
querying for a small set of individual
rows but in an olap use case what you're
often doing is you're querying over a
lot of data and so there are column
column store type format makes a lot of
sense there are actually extensions for
postgres now that do to store data in
columnar format but generally speaking I
would say postgres is very relative for
ltp and in some cases suit for olap now
when I look at this from performance
optimization perspective it again comes
back to query plans right so when I
optimize a query plan for an OTP
workload I would usually have a very
simple query I imagine in many cases
where it's more a question of how do I
squeeze out that last remaining bit of
performance versus an olap case usually
it's very complex queries that join a
lot of data or that scan a lot of data
and so if you have the right set of
indexes you can certainly improve both
right so indexes matter for both all app
and oltp but I would say in the case of
OTP you might be able to more purposely
build an index just for the particular
report or through generating once a day
for example versus in the case of
multi-p where you have just small fast
queries all the time you really want to
look at the whole workload right so you
really want to look at all the queries
that have run in the last seven days or
last 30 days and then get a sense for
what are they querying for right what
are they filtering for and then optimize
for that kind of set of queries versus
just individual queries
you mentioned there might be cases where
you need to switch to a more specialized
database I'm guessing you've done your
performance analysis and there just is
no knob to turn there's just nothing to
make it faster is that an experience
you've had where you just don't find a
solution even though you can see the
problem
I would think about what problem you're
trying to solve right so maybe a good
analogy if this would be if I'm
analyzing data that's just stored
internally and you know I'm just doing a
report across all the data right so most
of my reports are loading up all the
information then to be honest I don't
think postgres is a good use case for
that right if you're looking at all of
your data most of the time postgres will
be having more overheads than other
systems if you have columnist or again
column stores just by Design have less
overhead and even if you use the column
or extension for postgres that would
still not be as good as a purpose-built
system however the big benefit of
postgres would be that it integrates
better with other things you have right
so coming back to this old TP versus old
lab comparison with people in the last
years essentially have created is the
term htap and so h-type is kind of a
hybrid where you have some OTP type
queries and some or OLED type queries
and so what it matters is because you're
not going to choose a purpose-built
database that's good at data warehousing
when you're also doing you know
individual OTP type queries this was
actually something back when it was a
cytus data that we saw a lot what cytos
was good at is and why people choose
cytus over other Solutions was that they
had a mix of workloads so they had a use
case where they wanted to be able to do
some analysis across their whole
workholder across subsets of the
workload but then they also had
individual users just adding records and
doing inserts and so that type of stuff
is where postgres is really good at is
combining these type of approaches but
if I had just just olap I would probably
pick something else very popular these
days for example is Click
and that can make sense in many cases I
was referencing Century earlier today
just in our own tools that we use in
Century for example adopted clickhouse
for parts of the workload internally
they're also using postgres for other
parts right so they essentially started
using both data stores because that made
sense right it gave them the best
solution to combine them
let's dive into indexing probably one of
the most important aspects of database
performance just from a high level
how do you make the decision about
which types to index what type of index
to make whether to have an index how do
you decide these things sure and let's
maybe before we dive into the how to
make the decision maybe for those of you
who are not familiar with all the
different index types and postgres maybe
just a quick repeat of that so your most
common index type in postgres would be B
tree Index right and the way to think
about a b tree is essentially it helps
you optimize filtering as well as
sorting for your data so a lot of times
when your query for example when you
have no indexes it's maybe the best
comparison so one of the index choices
is no index and then what you're doing
is you're essentially looking at a large
file that stores all your data and
you're just going through it row by row
and you're filtering each row and you're
saying does this row match the query and
if it matches it returns if it doesn't
match it doesn't return and so the B
tree index is is essentially a cached
data structure that optimizes that
lookup so that you don't have to
manually go through each row and it does
that very well which is I would say 90
of cases you should use B tree index
there's of course other index types and
we don't necessarily have to go into all
the details today but just be aware that
for example in postgres when you're
doing lookups like does this value is
included in this array for example you
would want to use a gen index when
you're working for geospatial data you
might want to use it just index or SP
just index in some cases for all the P
workloads that actually make sense to
use hash indexes and so there's just
different index types with different
trade-offs that factor into your
indexing decisions
now kind of coming back to your question
of how do we reason about this right how
do we essentially make a choice of
indexes to me like the way I look at
indexing is essentially it is it is the
developer's job right so I think that
maybe the first important thing to note
is I don't think that indexes are the
dba's job or the devops job I think it's
a develop application engineer's job to
create the right indexes and so the way
to think about that for me is you're
writing your code right your code makes
orm calls these orm calls produce SQL
queries and these SQL queries ultimately
look for data in the database now when
you're trying to decide which index to
create really you need to be thinking
about the queries you're making right
you need to be thinking about what are
those queries filtering by
so when I do a select from a table or
your or M doesn't select from a table
you have a where clause and then it says
where column one equals something and
column b equals something else right
really that is the most important piece
because this is something that the
database will not do for you right the
database will not look at these where
Clauses and say oh they're always
querying for this set of look rare
Clauses I'll create Index right that is
a responsibility to the application
engineer has and so really it comes down
to which queries are you running would
where Clauses do they have that they're
filtering by and then if you want to get
you know more advanced which join
conditions are you using and which order
conditions like how are you sorting your
data because the best performance is
going to be when you look at a
combination of all the conditions you're
filtering by as well as the order in
which you want your data returned
because an index can both filter the
data but it can also give you a sorted
result and you can really get tremendous
performance improvements if you get this
right can actually share a specific
example that I worked with recently
where we had a case where there was a
400x performance performance actually
414x performance Improvement where we
took a query from 1.2 seconds so roughly
1 300 milliseconds to 3.13 milliseconds
um so huge Improvement and as I
referenced earlier right interactive
page loads might be 200 seconds right so
you could see how you know before with
when it took 39 seconds it was actually
milliseconds it was actually too slow
right somebody would have actually had a
slow experience versus that indexing
change actually made a difference and it
tremendously improved that query
performance to the point that was
actually interactive and that is really
why I think it matters to look at the
whole stack right because it doesn't
matter what code you're running on the
application side if you're making that
single SQL query and that turns out to
be that slow right then suddenly
everything else is going to feel
sluggish so you mentioned several
different types of indexes
is B tree the default or does postgres
automatically select any of these other
index types in certain cases
betray is the default so beachy is if
you don't tell postgres which index type
to use it's just going to give you B3
index which I think contributes to the
fact that most people have feature
indexes the thing also to note there is
index types relate to the operators you
use in your queries so when you I
mentioned earlier this example if you
have column A equals some value right so
the equal sign that's the operator
you're using in that case another
example would be if you have a not equal
sign that would be something that a
regular betray index cannot index well
actually it can I think filter in some
cases but it doesn't work well and
there's other operators and postgres
like your like containment operator or
in Json B for example you're saying you
know give me these jsonp documents that
match certain conditions which again a
B3 index isn't a good fit for and so
postgres will not make that choice for
you you actually have to tell postgres
create index and you say using and by
default if you don't specify using it's
essentially assumed to be using B tree
but you could just as well say using gin
or using gist or using for example PG
Vector is IVF flat as a particular index
type that the PG Vector extension
introduced so that's a totally different
index type for you know Vector embedding
type data so you mentioned operators
there's something called operator
classes does that have to do with
choosing an index also
I would argue most people listening to
this hopefully don't ever have to worry
about operator classes
so the the quick version of it is that
an operator class is essentially the
behind the scenes implementation of how
postgres would match up things right so
how postgres would when you have this
operator in your query how it will
ultimately get back to this index type
supports this operator class and then
supports you know this operator so it's
part of what the you know with postgres
itself will do during planning I think
in practice what most people will do is
they will create an index they'll run
and explain on it and then they'll
realize the index isn't used right and
so Danielle will hopefully realize that
part of the problem is that that
operator is not supported there's
actually a good overview also in the
postgres wiki if you look at particular
index types the postgres wiki or the
post documentation will actually tell
you which index type support which
operators and so I think it's really
more of a question of being diligent
right when you look at your queries and
you're not using an equals operator
because you're doing something else then
just understand that not all indexes
support all operators it's very specific
to which index type supports which
operator
yeah I can definitely relate to
documentation having Concepts which you
don't actually encounter as a end user
or or you may not have to deal with you
mentioned Json B
that is a binary format for Json that
postgres stores do you know anything
about the history of that it seems like
when I used it I didn't really
appreciate that it's a pretty
significant addition to the database
because you can store large Blobs of
Json and query into that Json do you
know much about how that came about
sure I know some of it I think there's
definitely other folks that you know are
the experts on it that you know actually
did the work here but my understanding
of the history is that so if you recall
you know maybe 10 years ago no SQL is
all the rage right everybody was like oh
stop using SQL stop using relational
databases we'll just do mongodb and you
know do lookups with on Json data and
we've obviously you know come around
since then right so nosql kind of tied
off as a concept in these days some
people using wrong would be some people
using postgres and what Jason B really
did is it brought this concept of
document stores to postgres now the
history here is that if you look back
many postgres versions like postgres 8
something there was just a text data
type right so if I had Json type data I
would just use the text like data type
and postgres I would just put it in text
column obviously I could do a lookup on
that text column right if I wanted to
match the whole document but I couldn't
really query inside the document now
after the text type which was always
there essentially the Json type got
introduced I think roughly maybe 15
years ago I think slightly more actually
maybe 18 years ago and so what the Json
type did is it essentially gave
validation to that data type so you
actually had the fact that this was a
Json structured document but it was
instilled essentially text inside
postgres now what Jason B is doing it's
very similar to what mongodb is doing
with I think there will be some internal
representation which is it's essentially
creating as I understand parts of the
Json are essentially stored differently
and they're stored differently in order
to enable faster lookups on the data and
also to in to be able to index the data
so it's essentially making making part
of the like for example the fact that
you have an integer versus text value in
your Json document gets represented in a
particular way and that then enables the
database to actually work efficiently on
it and what you know jsonp really
enables for you is that you're able to
do things like let's say you have a
column and you have Json document in
that column and it's a set of key and
value Pairs and you want to look up a
particular key and so in postgres you
can essentially just say newer versions
you can actually use the dot syntax and
older versions you would do an arrow and
then you would say the key name and then
it would give you that particular value
that the key references and so that is
something you can index in Json B
columns right so you can create an index
that optimizes this type of lookup and
that is enabled by having jsonp as that
kind of binary structured form of Json
in the database
so when using Json B is it ever
necessary to pull out a key and put it
in as a full class column as sort of for
is that faster access or do you is it
totally fine to just have all your data
be in the Json and and query in it yeah
I would I would definitely recommend if
you're always querying for a particular
column it's better to not have it in a
Json B because what you're essentially
doing is you're repeating all of these
keys and you're also incurring some
overhead just like lookups they're fast
but they're not as fast as a regular
column and so if like usually what I see
and what I think is the best practice is
if you have unstructured data that is
different between your different rows
right so some customers have this data
some customers have the other ones then
Json B is a great fit if you always have
a particular column then I would not put
it in a jsonp field I would actually put
it in a regular column because that is
going to be the best performance it's
going to have the least data storage
requirements and so essentially that mix
is the best practice I've seen that's
kind of what I expected when I when I
was using it
how about expression indexes that seems
like another index type or is that a
aspect of indexing yeah I would say it's
an aspect of indexing so expression
indexes one thing that's cool about
postgres postgres has you know a lot of
Versatility in how you can do things and
so expression indexes are essentially a
way for you to index not just a single
column right so when I do create index I
choose what to index and so usually I
would say this column or multiple
columns right which there's certain
trade-offs on that but let's say we're
querying our users table and we're
always like we're comparing an email
address and so usually what I've seen is
that people want to compare email
addresses lowercase right because if
somebody signs in with their email
address typed uppercase versus lowercase
you kind of want to match the same way
and so in your query you would have
selects are from users where lower email
equals a certain value now what postgres
would do usually is if you had just an
index on the column email it would
actually not be able to use the index
because the lookup you're doing is not
on email email is on the lower function
on that email column and so an
expression index lets you do is it lets
you index that expression and so you can
actually essentially index the result of
the lower function in this case on the
email and so your index will just have
all the lowercase emails and so that way
all the lookups are going to be fast
because you're actually going to be able
to match the index to that particular
query now unfortunately the inverse also
doesn't work so if you have an index an
expression index on Lower email if you
just do a regular query with just email
without that function you're not going
to be able to use the Expression Index
right so it's very particular to how you
queries are structured how your workload
works and you really got to understand
which queries you're running to be able
to to make those choices essentially
whether to use expression indexes or not
how about PG analyzes index advisor how
did that feature come about and how does
it work as a developer sure and it came
about as a
essentially this exact challenge right
like if I'm if I'm an engineer I don't
think about individual queries usually
right I essentially write code add a new
feature and then that feature has
queries Associated to it but I don't
really think of that day to day and so
the motivation behind index advisor is
that your kind of you know feature
development ultimately produces queries
and those queries ultimately run against
your database and oftentimes people
don't add the right indexes because it's
not something that's always part of the
engineering practice oftentimes what
happens is people do a best effort right
they would try to understand well maybe
this is a right index type but they're
not really looking at the whole query
workload that's the motivation behind
our work on index advisor is that what
if we took all your query workload right
all the queries that you've run in a
database we split it up into what we
call scans which are essentially on this
table I'm filtering for this set of
conditions that's a scan for us across
you know all your queries across all
these scans we would then say what is
the right set of indexes to choose now
this is not a novel idea actually like
this idea I think maybe 30 years ago was
there was a paper already on the problem
of index selection right so index
selection itself is generally a a
problem that people have encountered all
the time with relational databases I
think what's unique in our approach here
is that what we're actually doing first
of all we're doing it for postgres so if
you use SQL server today SQL server has
a built-in feature for index
recommendations but postgres itself does
not have anything built in so first of
all it's in postgres the second thing is
we are doing this across your whole
workload not across individual queries
so if you are interested in individual
queries there is for example the hypo PG
extension in postgres hyper Fiji lets
you say if I have this query and if this
hypothetical index existed what would be
the cost of the query right so the
planning cost that we talked about
earlier and so hyper PG is a very
important building block to what we're
doing but it is is just a piece right
and really what we're trying to solve is
that I would say that mental overhead
that application Engineers have when
they think of query workloads right when
I I mean I'm just looking at our own
database and is like thousands of
queries and so I'm not going to go
through each and every single query and
look at the where Clause like that's
just way too tedious right it just takes
too much time I mean so what we
essentially said how can we do better
right how can we actually make this be a
better experience for the engineers
I think we could spend the whole show on
indexing but there are some other topics
I want to try to get to although we're
probably will refer back to indices in
some cases so let's talk about queries
in the sense of what performance
problems can we fixed just by changing
the SQL query itself so not database
configuration not table configuration
not indices but just more or less you
wrote the SQL poorly I guess do those
types of situations happen
these type of situations definitely
happen there's definitely a lot of cases
that are not indexes I just want to make
one less remark on indexes which is
sometimes when you are not having an
index being used the change you should
make is not at an index but change your
query right so sometimes it actually
makes sense to rewrite the query so that
you are matching your existing indexes
one example of this would be partial
indexes which just know that this is a
problem and if you if if you don't see
your Nexus being used just make sure
you're matching your partial indexes the
one thing I would say if it's if we're
not talking indexing the other cases
that I've seen is oftentimes one problem
for example is regarding pagination so
one very common class of problem queries
that I've observed is when you have an
application right and you're showing a
list of like results essentially in a
search and then you're not just throwing
the first page but you may be showing
the fifth page and from a user
perspective usually what you would want
is you know a page one page two page
three page four right and you click on
the fifth page and it shows you the
fifth page results usually how you
implement this on the postgres side is
you do limit an offset that if you've
ever read anything I would limit an
offset then there's essentially a group
of people that say offset is bad you
should not be using it because what
postgres will do so let's say I I'm
saying postgres give me the fifth page
of results right postgres will actually
fetch all of the results and then
paginate in that result set to give you
that offset of let's say each page is
100 results right well giving the
results between like results 400 and
result 500 right and we're giving you
these 100 records it had to also load
the other records right before that and
so oftentimes in terms of rewriting
queries the change you can make here
which unfortunately has been invasive
but it's really big performance
Improvement is instead of doing limit
and Offset you would actually change
your where Clause to look up what's
called key set based pagination where
you're saying give me all the records
that are larger than this ID number are
larger than this identifier and that's
going to be much faster from a query
perspective but you do have to change
your query to benefit from that you
mentioned partial indexes and I did read
about that where you could index for
example only non-null rows was a simple
case given and I imagine it could get
much more complicated than that how
about views and materialized views are
those things that any query should
consider using for performance
so I would say views don't really give
you a benefit in performance they really
give you a benefit in terms of kind of
abstracting your data better right so if
you have a lot of like you find yourself
especially when you're running manual
queries right so it's more actually olap
use case where you find yourself writing
queries and you always have this really
complex query that always looks the same
it always you know maybe joins the same
things and you just want to have a
easier way of querying then a view will
help you do that because it extracts the
essentially it's a it's a rewrite of
your queries it's a simplification of
your query it's kind of like a function
call you could say right so you're kind
of simplifying your query into a shorter
form and you can just say select from
View and then it will automatically
translate into a much more complex query
what materialized views do on the other
hand materialized views are a cached
version of that data so instead of the
data being retrieved at query time it
actually gets stored in that form and so
the materialist view can have a
performance benefit the big downside
with imperialized views is that they get
refreshed explicitly not automatically
and so it's something that you have to
like you say create material as view on
a particular query then the materialist
view will cache that data but then the
problem is if you want the up-to-date
data you do need to say refresh
materialized view um to get the updated
version in new approaches of postgres
that's actually there's a version of
this called refresh materialist view
concurrently which if you are on that
version it supports it definitely use
that version usually in postgres
concurrently means it takes less locks
so it has less overhead essential in
database if you use the version without
concurrently it will actually block
activity on that view so if you have
queries that try to query the
materialized view they will actually be
blocked for that refresh so that's just
something to watch out for when you're
doing a lot of refreshes so I'm guessing
cte's Common Table expressions are like
views and that it's not directly a
performance concern but
maybe they do let you write longer and
longer queries is there any impact
you've seen from cet's on performance so
CTS are interesting because they they're
different depending on which pulse Chris
version you're looking at so with CTE
for those of you not familiar would be
essentially in an individual query let's
say I'm joining like I'm doing select
star from my table and then I want to
join against some other data and the
other data is not just a single table
but it's maybe some other complex query
that I want to run so CTE lets you
abstract that so that you could actually
write with and you say my data as and
then you have a query a sub query that
is all the data you want to work with
and then later on your reference that
CTE again in the same query now in older
postgres versions what postgres would
actually do is it would materialize the
CTE so materializing not in the sense of
a materialized view which is actually
stored on disk but just materializing in
terms of storing it in memory so that it
would first run that CTE query that
subselect remember the result of that
and then run a query like the other
parts of the query against it now in
postgres 12 if I recall correctly they
change this so that instead of a CTE
always being materialized you can now
either say with the name of CTE as
materialized or not materialized so you
can kind of control the behavior or if
you don't explicitly specify it postgres
will actually choose what to do now the
reason that this was the change was made
is because oftentimes this
materialization component of ctes
actually works against you because
you're essentially preventing postgres
from doing certain optimizations and how
to choose the square plans and so in
newer postgres versions oftentimes it's
actually a benefit to have that
materialization not happen but sometimes
when you are trying to run your query in
a certain way you would actually want
the materialization and so then it does
matter to actually add that keyword so
that you are explicitly materializing
and then later essentially reference
just a cached result
maybe I should have asked this first but
how about just join itself the bread and
butter of relational databases what
sorts of performance implications are
there and how you perform and join I'm
guessing maybe it's the order a join
with b or B join with a or what ways are
there to do this better or or worse
no you you're right so the I think the
the most important choice so when you're
joining your tables the most important
choice that the postgres planner has to
make is which order to join the tables
in and then the second most important
choice is how to join right now for the
join order there's various ways postgres
does it I would say the most surprising
thing to know is so join order is
actually quite expensive to calculate
because it when you try to find the
optimum join order you need to
understand the costs of all the
different variants and so postgres will
actually switch over to a different way
of planning if I think by default you
have more than 10 join tables so if
you're drawing more in 10 tables post
because we'll actually do something
special be aware of that
um there's certain settings that relate
to that and so once postgres has you
know found the join order that works it
also looks at the join method that is
using the three join methods that exist
are either hash joins merge joints or
nested Loop joins you can always use a
nested Loop so nested Loop just means
get the data for one of the tables and
then iterate over each row and find data
for the other table because the
iteration nested Loops can be quite slow
because you're essentially if you have
two big tables and you've got two big
result sets you will have one table
where you're doing a lot of small kind
of queries into the table versus merge
joins and hash joins what they do is
they load the two kind of results
separately and then merge or hash join
them together and so that way it's much
faster essentially from a just pure you
know lookup perspective because it's a
much simpler lookup to do
okay that was some about queries how
about
maintenance created that category
maintenance
one topic there I found was vacuuming as
an application developer it sounds a lot
like garbage collection is that
something that your tool is able to
monitor or recommend how to configure
that I guess
so we are actually in the process of
launching we call the peach anal as a
vacuum advisor and so vacuuming for
those of you who don't know is
essentially I like the garbage
collection is one with looking at
vacuuming is essentially defragmentation
right so the way to think about it the
way the postgres does things when you're
doing an update statement or delete
statement the old version that you no
longer need is still on disk and so what
vacuuming does is it cleans up that old
version of the road now some of you
might ask why don't we just remove the
data right away right if I'm doing a
delete why do we keep the old data
around and really the answer to that is
the way how postgres determines
visibility so if you have multiple
concurrent connections it might be that
another connection is still able to see
that row that you're just deleting and
so that's why it's so important that
postgres doesn't just delete it right
away it actually kind of keeps it around
for a bit longer until nothing else sees
it and then vacuum essentially cleans
that up
now what I found is that vacuum and
postgres is one of those maintenance
commands that are actually really like
it seemed really simple but it gets
really complicated what gets really
complicated is so postgres has a process
called Auto vacuum and what Auto vacuum
does is essentially it's a if you think
of it as a more advanced version of a
Cron job that runs on your tables and it
will run the vacuum command on your
tables on the schedule but the schedule
is not just every day at five but
instead the schedule is when a certain
condition is met then run the vacuum and
there's a lot of different conditions
the most important one to know is that
if there's a number of dead rows right
so if your number of deletes for example
or a number of updates then at some
point vacuum will kick in Auto vacuum
will kick in and will actually clean up
that data and essentially make the space
reusable and so if you're seeing your
table size grow and grow and grow and
kind of become bloated then oftentimes
the issue is that your auto vacuum is
not running often enough it's not
actually cleaning up the data now what
we found is that we already collect a
lot of useful data about this in PG
analyze but so far we haven't really
made tuning recommendations and so our
new vacuum advisor essentially gives you
tuning recommendations where it
specifically says for this table tweak
this threshold to run back in more
frequently to avoid bloat accumulating
and we do that based on essentially
looking at the data we're receiving is
kind of projecting if vacuum ran more
frequently would bloat have been avoided
and then we kind of make your
recommendation to change these table
specific settings
another maintenance task might be
backups I almost feel like some
application developers these days just
expect their database to be redundant
and essentially never have to restore
from backups but I imagine other people
still do regular backups what are the
performance and implications of backups
in terms of how do you not degrade the
user perceived performance
I think the good news as you say most
people don't have to worry about backups
today right so if you are in the cloud I
think what matters most is you
understand what your company's backup
policy is right like how long backups
should be kept and make sure your
databases actually keep it that long I
don't really think you have to worry
much about the whole database backup in
that sense what is I think helpful to
understand is if you're doing a PG dump
on your database that is of course
actually incurring performance so the
big difference here is what I'll call a
physical backup versus a logical backup
and so a logical backup would be PG dump
which actually runs queries against your
database versus a physical backup
essentially reads files and certainly if
you ran PG dump what would happen is you
would produce a slow query it's
essentially a select star on your table
and so that could have some overhead it
will have overhead because you are kind
of getting all the data you're copying
all data into postal shared buffers and
then you're returning to the client
essentially and so that's just slow and
so that's something that you want to
watch out for if you have a large
database it's usually best practice not
to do that you might want to use a
replica right and if have a replica that
then you run PG dump on okay speaking of
replica how about just a little comment
on scaling in general so I think I
mentioned this at the beginning you have
some
user load and it's gotten 10 times or
100 times bigger and your performance is
suffering and two options in most
back-end cases are sort of horizontal or
vertical scaling
how am I going to decide which of these
is going to solve my problem or or what
combination of these because that seems
like a pretty big operational question
yeah I can recall also from my
experience back at cytus where we saw
this problem a lot so the way we solve
this back outside is was we essentially
had this extension for postgres which
would let you run multiple postgres
servers and essentially you could think
of your whole you know set of servers as
ones you could run a query like again
for example select star and it could
actually go across the nodes
transparently behind the scenes that is
obviously the most scalable approach
right because you can just add more
nodes like if you want more scalability
you just add another node sometimes
people solve this also on the
application side where they do sharding
and then the application does the
routing between the different nodes so
if you think of yourself as you know the
billion dollar company that needs to be
able to scale infinitely then certainly
thinking about a multi-node approach I
think is very useful the one thing I
would caution against there is I think
there's a trend towards making
everything a distributed database and I
think that is actually not a good choice
sometimes so the one thing that I recall
again from website is what we've done a
lot of times back then is we would
actually try to make queries go to a
single node as much as possible because
querying a large set of notes for your
queries is expensive and there is some
essentially speed of light constraints
also in terms of making sure that things
are consistent and so what you will
actually find is that some of these
databases that promise infinite
scalability and is all distributed they
actually end up being slower for very
small fast queries where it's actually
much better to have a single node you're
querying and so that's just something to
think about is are you doing a lot of
querying across nodes and if you are
doing that then can you partition your
data in a way so that doesn't happen
there's lots of details to this but I
would still personally recommend the
side this extension it's open source so
you can just you know install it in your
own server some of you know my
colleagues from back then are sold Azure
so they also offer managed service for
that how about partitioning is that
different than replicas in terms of
dividing up your data what is
partitioning I guess and what is the
upside or downside of partitioning so I
would say there's essentially three ways
of like if you go from a single table on
a single server right there's three ways
to scale it out so partitioning in the
simplest form can mean partitions in
postgres on a single server so that
means you do essentially have a regular
table but instead of you know this the
table being a single table on the server
it's actually multiple tables on the
same server so that oftentimes makes a
lot of sense partitioning in that sense
is useful when you're for example of
Time series data and you want to drop
old partitions that's really fast
operation and so partitioning will help
you manage large sets of data on a
single server better a variant of
partitioning is what we call sharding so
sharding essentially is when you are
splitting up your data but instead of
splitting it up on the same server you
are splitting it up across multiple
servers and this comes back to an
extension like cytus for example now the
Third Way of scaling out would be
replication this is something let's
imagine you have your AWS Aurora cluster
you can just add additional reader nodes
and so reader node in Aurora is just a
replica in postgres terms so that means
it's a full copy of your database that
essentially follows behind the primary
that you could use for queries the
challenge there of course is that you're
still limited to the performance of an
individual node so if your queries are
really expensive they're not going to
get faster by using replicas they're
just going to spread out more so if you
have too many queries that can be a way
to kind of scale out the read workload
great well we talked about indexing
queries maintenance scaling I have one
last topic to touch on and then we'll
start wrapping up I'm not sure how much
you have to say about this but I as an
application developer I'm kind of
interested in the concept of stored
procedures this almost sounds to me like
having your database run arbitrary code
how common are stored procedures today
and what languages can you use to write
them and
can you monitor their performance
because that starts to sound like
application performance monitoring and I
think so procedures are interesting like
procedures could either we create
procedure or create function and
postgres on a server side what's
interesting about them is I think I've
usually seen them in the workplace that
I see it's a lot of times migrations
from other database systems so if you
migrate from Oracle to postgres or SQL
Server to postgres that's where I see a
lot of people like a lot of old school
databases so to say use procedures to
encode business Logic on the database
and it kind of has grown out of fashion
since then I think right so if you
looked at applications within the last
10 years most of the time people don't
do that same level of putting business
logic in a database I think part of it
has to do with just you know the
functions on a database site being more
constrained in terms of Which languages
you can use but also harder to debug now
there is a trend actually where that's
changing a bit so most recently there
was an extension release called PL rust
and pl is it stands for programming or
procedural language and so postgres
actually has a system that's extendable
for using different languages and so for
example if you want to write JavaScript
in your postgres there's plv8 which is
the V8 JavaScript engine if you want to
run python in your post because there's
PL Python and recently there's PL of us
now what's notable of appeal rust is
that it's a community project that you
know essentially to focus around the
pgrx extension framework started which
lets you write
sea level extensions essentially put in
Rust now PL rust is a trusted language
or aims to provide a trusted language
what trusted languages mean is that it's
really meant for application code that
run runs the database versus you
extending a database server and so
what's really nice about PL rust is that
specifically Amazon RDS also added
support for that recently so if you are
an RDS you can actually now deploy your
rust functions to you know your RDS
database as well using plrust now if we
think about how we want to debug the
performance of that that's where it gets
a bit tricky so there are ways to track
function performance on postgres so you
can they will show up as a query right
so just the fact that you know query
runs will show up and then each function
will also kind of when it runs queries
itself inside the function these queries
will also be visible in tools like PG
stat statements and through that will
also be visible in PG analyze for
example but where it gets tricky is when
you have very complex functions
oftentimes the tooling today is a bit
lacking and the tooling really on the
postgres side unfortunately to reference
back which part of the function caused
which query to be slow and so it
actually becomes a bit harder to debug
and so I personally don't do a lot of
putting logic into functions that do a
lot of stuff on the database side just
because of that extra level of
interaction making it harder to reason
about hard to profile and so that's kind
of you know I would say use with caution
but if it if you have a workload where
this makes sense there is definitely
good options today to do it
I was kind of relieved when you said
it's potentially going out of style it
sounds like super powerful but also very
potentially very hard to manage in terms
of your application logic being split
and partially on the database yep that's
exactly right so let's start wrapping up
what's next for PG analyze say what
features are coming this year or
community events or just what are you
looking forward to in PG analyze and
then we'll talk about postgres for sure
yeah so I think for us at PG analyze
it's really more about how can we make
postgres smarter how can we make
postgres work better for you right as an
application engineer so we are about to
launch our new vacuum advisor which will
you know kind of give you the right per
table tuning insights we just gave a
talk at peachycon in Ottawa which was
finally an in-person conference again
after many years and so there we talked
about new index selection algorithm and
so we're going to release a new version
of index advisor later this year that
features that new constrained
programming based model for index
advisor and then generally I think with
the way you're looking at this is how
can we give you the right data at the
right time right so ideally how can we
notify you and alert you of a problem on
your database proactively that really
ties to specific queries or ties to
specific indexes or tables for example
yeah just as an aside I think one of
your
features was notifying you about a
problem before it gets bad so there is a
dashboard that you can set up alarms
with and and just kind of keep an eye on
things that's right yeah and it's like
one practice that I've seen especially
larger companies where you have you know
data platform teams adopt is that
they've actually adopted PG analyst as a
way to get slack notifications so we'll
actually put you know here's a new
missing index and we'll put that in your
slack channel for your individual
application teams which is really useful
just you know take a little bit of a
burden off of that Central data team
that today has a lot of the manual work
here so just a question of getting the
data to the right people in the rights
Channel
how about postgres itself is there any
major releases coming up particularly
related to Performance or just any
features you're looking forward to there
yeah so postgres is on a generally a
yearly release Cadence and so we'll have
the postgres 16 release that's currently
in beta will probably come out in
September or October that's the usual
schedule depends a bit on the release
candidates and if there's any major
bucks found in postgres 17 development
has started now the branch just opened
about a month ago and so what's really
exciting for me I think in 16 from a
performance optimization perspective
there's a new way of getting statistics
about the i o kind of performance of the
system so there's a view called PG
statio the Melanie plagueman kind of
contributed to postgres and what that
new new view really does is it lets you
say which part of the system is creating
i o right so it lets you say well is it
the vacuuming is it the queries is it
something else that's causing things to
be slow and so you kind of have this
high level you know kind of birds eye
view on the whole database activity that
you didn't really have before and again
it's coming out in postgres 16 and I
think well extend Pidgeot is to read
that view and kind of provide insights
based on that as well in postgres 17
which is currently under development I'm
really excited about asynchronous IO
there's a lot of work ongoing behind the
scenes about asynchronous IO and how it
makes the database faster we'll see how
much actually you know gets into
postgres 17 so there's obviously no bit
of ambiguity early in the development
cycle but I think what Andres freund and
Thomas Monroe and team have worked on
there there's some really interesting
kind of patches being worked on for
postgres
great where can people read more about
you and PG analyze and even postgres I'm
curious if there's any niches in the
community you can point to that are
interesting to follow I know it's such a
big project might be a little
intimidating to people just curious how
you found the community and what you
what resources you like to use for sure
so let's start with Focus so I think
what I read which I would if you're
really into it what I would encourage
you reading is the postgres hackers
mailing list so the hackers mailing list
is kind of it's like the Linux kernel
mailing list or the llvm project mailing
list so it's very technical very a lot
of deeply technical content but that's
where all the development for postgres
happens right so postgres is a community
project it's not a single company behind
it it's many people contributing and so
you will see each and every decision
being made out of the open essentially
and so that's really fascinating to
observe and just to read the mailing
list again this PG SQL hackers which you
can find on the postgres and project
mailing list list otherwise I would say
you know we a future analyst for example
if you're interested in just you know
what's new with postgres we actually
record a weekly series called five
minutes of postgres where I'm
essentially featuring what's new with
postgres so if you just want to keep up
with postgres things you can subscribe
to five minutes of postgres on YouTube
and then if you're interested in PG
analyze we have a newsletter that we
send out each month we also I for
example have a message on account we
have a Twitter account for PG allies so
if you want to follow us on social media
sites um that's of course an option as
well and in general feel free to email
us anytime we generally try to be
approachable and answer any questions
you have about what we're doing or what
we're talking about
excellent and I'll put links to all
those in the show notes thanks Lucas for
your time today of course thank you
Phillip this is Philip Winston for
software engineering radio
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]